<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on I dream, therefore I am</title>
    <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on I dream, therefore I am</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://xwcal.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Groups, rings, Bézout&#39;s identity, modular arithmetic and self-closing loop generators</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/07/10/self_closing_loop_generators/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/07/10/self_closing_loop_generators/</guid>
      <description>1 Introduction Daniel Fedorin investigated an intriguing phenomenon where rich patterns arise out of an extremely simple algorithm:&#xA;Generate a finite sequence of integers, then iterate though the sequence repeatedly: at each step, draw a line segment of that integer length and then turn a fixed angle. This post extends Daniel&#39;s excellent work and delves deeper into the math behind this magic 1.&#xA;Here is a demo for those who have yet to appreciate the magic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unwalling the NP-completeness of multi-commodity integral flow</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/23/multi-commodity_integral_flow_np_complete/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/23/multi-commodity_integral_flow_np_complete/</guid>
      <description>While ruminating on the difficulty of irreducible saw patterns, I took another look at Fortune et al. and noticed the following mention of On the complexity of time table and multi-commodity flow problems by Even et al.:&#xA;We note that the result of Even, Itai and Shamir [2] on multicommodity flows implies that the directed subgraph homeomorphism problem is NP-complete if both pattern and input graphs are given as input, even if the input graph is acyclic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detour problem&#39;s next challenge: irreducible saw patterns</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/21/detour_problem_next_challenge_irreducible_saw_patterns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/21/detour_problem_next_challenge_irreducible_saw_patterns/</guid>
      <description>To facilitate our discussion, let&#39;s expand the existing definitions and make a few things formal. For u,v \in V $u,v \in V$, let&#39;s refer to a simple path in G-\mathcal{B}_{s,t}+u+v $G-\mathcal{B}_{s,t}+u+v$ (ie. completely outside \mathcal{B}_{s,t} $\mathcal{B}_{s,t}$ except the end points) from u $u$ to v $v$ as a hop from u $u$ to v $v$. We say it is forward if dist(s,u) $dist(s,u) &lt; dist(s,v)$, lateral if dist(s,u) = dist(s,v) $dist(s,u) = dist(s,v)$, and backward if dist(s,u) &gt; dist(s,v) $dist(s,u) &gt; dist(s,v)$.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bugfix: detour problem solution needs [not] transitive closure</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/07/detour_problem_bugfix_trans_closure/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/07/detour_problem_bugfix_trans_closure/</guid>
      <description>Bugfix EDIT 20240408: What can I say about a bad brain fart? Guess there is no substitute for letting an idea sit for a while, preferably over at least a night of sound sleep, so that I get a chance to see my own mistakes. In going from one extreme (research, but never publish) to another, I have removed the gate that keeps my mistakes from escaping into the wild. Despite the cost (confusion to my readers, if any, and embarrassment to myself), I will keep this experiment going: this is the first time I do research completely in the open and document the process as I go.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bugfix: detour problem solution should search for fork/join</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/02/detour_problem_bugfix/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/04/02/detour_problem_bugfix/</guid>
      <description>Bugfix The previous algorithm contains a flagrant bug 1 that managed to elude my attention. Here is an updated version with VDJ-122 and VDJ-221 modified (the definitions in my previous post are a prerequisite):&#xA;For u, v \in \mathcal{B}_{s,t} $u, v \in \mathcal{B}_{s,t}$, u \neq v $u \neq v$:&#xA;If dist_{G-\mathcal{B}_{s,t}+u+v}(u,v) $dist_{G-\mathcal{B}_{s,t}+u+v}(u,v) &lt; \infty$:&#xA;If dist(s,u) \le dist(s,v) $dist(s,u) \le dist(s,v)$:&#xA;Return True&#xA;Elif VDJ-122(\mathcal{B}_{s,t}, s, u, v) $(\mathcal{B}_{s,t}, s, u, v)$ and</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ending a detour: [not] solving an open problem in 17 days</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/03/30/detour_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/03/30/detour_problem/</guid>
      <description>1 The detour problem The statement given by Antoine Amarilli is rephrased here:&#xA;Given a directed graph G = (V,E) $G = (V,E)$, a source s \in V $s \in V$ and a target t \in V $t \in V$ reachable from s $s$, decide if there a simple directed path from s $s$ to t $t$ whose length (in terms of edge count) is greater than that of the shortest path from s $s$ to t $t$.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum observer paradox</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/03/28/quantum_observer_paradox/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/03/28/quantum_observer_paradox/</guid>
      <description>Suppose we have a Stern-Gerlach device exhibiting particle-like behavior 1, such that in the x $x$ direction, we have a complete basis: \{ |measure_{+x}\rangle, |measure_{-x}\rangle \} $\{ |measure_{+x}\rangle, |measure_{-x}\rangle \}$, akin to a spin-\frac{1}{2} $\frac{1}{2}$ particle, which has \{ |spin_{+x}\rangle, |spin_{-x}\rangle \} $\{ |spin_{+x}\rangle, |spin_{-x}\rangle \}$.&#xA;Suppose the Stern-Gerlach device is configured as in Feynman&#39;s beautiful exposition 2 to block the lower beam, allowing only particles that take the upper route to fly through.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jane Street Puzzle solution: Robot Long Jump</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/02/29/jane-st-202303-robot-long-jump-solution/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/02/29/jane-st-202303-robot-long-jump-solution/</guid>
      <description>Recently I found in my drawer some five pages of scribble dating back to Mar 2023, of my solution to that month&#39;s Jane Street Puzzle 1. Working on the puzzle was a wonderful process of meditation in a time of turmoil, and of reliving the peaceful memories of an aspiring student of math, statistics and computer science 2.&#xA;Somewhat surprisingly, I was able to recall the techniques in calculus and probability theory I hadn&#39;t touched for years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few words on exponentiation</title>
      <link>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/on-exponentiation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://xwcal.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/on-exponentiation/</guid>
      <description>Although MathJax dominates today&#39;s html+latex landscape, I always feel reader-side rendering of latex leaves much to be desired.&#xA;After getting my writer-side svg generation and embedding engine up and running, I thought, why not write something to test drive it? So here it goes.&#xA;Mathematics First, note that a^b $a^b$ (a^b or a**b in most programming languages) is right associative. So, 2^{3^4} = 2^{81} $2^{3^4} = 2^{81}$, an enormous number of 25 digits, not (2^3)^4 $(2^3)^4$, which is merely 4096.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
